stabilizers
this is a really complex subject that
people avoid like the plague So today
we're going to briefly talk about what
they are what they do and how you use
them in ice cream
[Music]
hi everybody I'm Nick welcome back to
Polar Ice Creamery as we said at the
start we're going to talk about ice
cream stabilizers now a stabilizer is
something that has an effect on your ice
cream base the effect can be for various
reasons but the majority of them are to
reduce Ice Crystal size to reduce air
bubble size and to make your ice cream
smoother melt slower more evenly and to
make it creamy in the mouth so
this is just a few of the ones I've got
here I haven't got any commercial ones
here today
but let's talk about where they come
from
[Music]
so people are obsessed thinking that
stabilizers are an unnatural product and
I can kind of understand why because
governments have labeled them with
numbers e numbers now there are a lot of
unnatural products to have these labels
and that's I think what where people are
getting confused
but there is a reason for this e number
because it's an additive it's not a
direct food product so they can't label
it as well they can they could call it
what it is but if you saw
um you know guar gum locust bean gum in
your
in your food you'd probably freak out
thinking you're eating locusts but it's
not so by giving it these e numbers it
allows them to store a database of all
the products what they are and then
to take up less space on your ingredient
label they can just put the blah blah e
number on it
so the the majority of ice cream
stabilizers are like I said natural
products they come from Beans they come
from seaweed they come from plants they
come from fruit they come from all these
kind of things and and what they're
they're done is they're processed in
factories dried dehydrated
um they you know they might you might
have gelatin sheets all these kind of
things they're certainly not made up
through artificial chemicals so you can
kind of forget that straight away or the
ones that we're talking about here
aren't there are some that are
but the majority of the ones you're
going to use on ice cream are natural
products
so we'll start with this one ice cream
stabilizer this is a mix from straight
from special ingredients this is a
really good one if you can get I know
you can buy this on Amazon uh you can
buy on Amazon UK Amazon us Amazon Canada
so you know it's going to be available
most places it is quite expensive for
how much you get and if you were to
Source the ingredients yourself you'd be
able to make it cheaper but ultimately
if you want to buy something off the
shelf and use it in your ice cream at
home I'd probably start with something
like this there are other brands and
other mixes of ice cream stabilizer
available but this is the one that I use
what is in this so on a back it's locust
bean gum which is e410 fatty acids which
are e471 go our gun which is e412 sodium
alginate which is e401 and agar agar
which is
e406 so all those products are natural
products but they've all got that e
number for regulation purposes
don't let that ski Okay so
let's just talk about each individual
element
Locus being done
what is locust bean gum where does it
come from and what does it do so Locus
being gum which is shortened in many
places to LBG is also known as carabin
flower and it's made from the seeds of
the carob tree
this is a tree that's quite common in
Mediterranean places and it's been used
as thickeners in cooking for hundreds if
not thousands of years
this is what a locust bean gum looks
like and during its stages of processing
it comes down into a powder just gets
pumice down into a really fine powder
now Locus bean gum is very popular
because it has one of the best Ice
Crystal reduction capabilities
what that means is that Locus bean gum
will assist with the reduction of Ice
Crystal size formation in your ice cream
so the longer your ice cream takes to
churn the larger those ice crystals can
get this helps with that if you have a
very cheap machine off Amazon for 20
pounds this will really help improve the
texture of your ice cream
now if you're also gonna let your ice
cream defrost before you start serving
it what you're doing is you're melting
some of those ice crystals which makes
it smoother and easier to scoop then
when you put it back in the freezer
you're refreezing them
that process increases the size of the
ice crystals so you're you're you've
gone through all the effort of making
ice cream it tastes really good you take
it out of the freezer you leave it for
10 minutes to soften up so you can scoop
it you're actually having a detrimental
effect on the overall texture of your
ice cream doing that so this is that's
where these come in because they start
to reduce that enlargement of ice
crystals
the next part of this mix is fatty acids
fatty acids we're going to look at silk
gel without silk gel is a mono and
diglycerides of fatty acids e471 on here
fatty acids e471 so that is what is in
here silk gel silk gel is you can see
that is literally a white slash clear
it's like semi-opaque let's call it that
it's got It's a semi-opaque gum this
actually although it is a stabilizer to
a degree it's more an emulsifier so this
will help your fats on your Waters
combine into a much smoother base but
they've added it in here so in a
powdered format so that you can have a
stabilized and emulsified ice cream base
again the emulsification makes your
final result ice cream smoother smoother
mouth feel smoother on the tongue
the emulsification helps to make your
base more viscous the viscosity of your
base has a direct relation to the size
of the air bubbles
the more viscous your ice cream base
increases the shear strength as your ice
cream churns so as your ice cream is
churning and getting harder and harder
and harder the viscosity increase shares
the actual ice cream itself in the
training process and shrinks the size of
the air bubbles smaller air bubbles much
like the smaller ice crystals give you a
nice smooth mouth feel so that's that
will help with that as well
the next ingredient is Gua gum I don't
have any guar gum on its own but I have
this which is my mix in here this is
just an old turbo recycled so this is a
locust bean gum and go our gum mixture
so it's two part Locus being gone one
part going
now go our gum again it's a natural
ingredient this is e412 and just so you
can see here e412 so it's the same
product now what is guar gum let's talk
about that shall we
so go our gum is derived from a seed of
The Gua plant that that is part of the
legume family so it is directly related
to peanuts now I don't know if you'd be
allergic to guagum if you are allergic
to peanuts that would be interesting to
know so if you are allergic to peanuts
maybe look at that first guagam has been
used in India for thousands of years and
it's been used as a stabilizer in ice
cream since the 1950s
now go welcome doesn't reduce the Ice
Crystal sizes as well as Locus bean gum
but it adds more viscosity now again
we're talking viscosity here like we
were with the silk gel the high
viscosity means smaller air bubbles
during the churning process
so if you had just your Locus being I'm
like I've done in here if you adjust
your Locus being gum and your guano gum
combined into one little handy tub what
you've got here is you've got the guar
gum to increase the viscosity so that
will reduce your air bubble size and
you've got the locust bean gum to reduce
your Ice Crystal size and the battery's
running up
so
overall then what you've got is a really
handy little mix you've got a handy mix
that accounts for two of those elements
the viscosity so reduced air bubble size
and the reduced Ice Crystal size
the next ingredient on here is sodium
algae I don't have any of that that
comes from seaweed but essentially it's
it has a similar kind of effect as a
garaga which is used in here as well but
what that does again is it increases
viscosity it comes from Brown ocean kelp
which is a cold water kelp itself it
dissolves in cold water but does hydrate
better around the 70 degrees Centigrade
Mark it's okay at keeping ice crystals
small
and it does contribute to a better
texture and body that some gums can't
create but I've never had a problem with
just using gums so if you want to avoid
sodium alginate and agara garden that's
absolutely fine
but as it's in this proprietary mix why
not just use it it's um
again it's it's off the shelf you don't
have to worry about it and the final one
agar agar like I said that that is this
I broke the tub so what is a garaga
the garaga is a natural vegetable
gelatin counterpart so it's good if
you're vegan and you don't want to use
you know animal-based gelatin you can
use a garaga you can use it in Jellies
as well it's really really good it's a
white semi-translucent when sold in
packages and it is really just a
thickening agent so if you're if you're
going to use a an ice cream base that
doesn't have a lot of body so let's say
you're looking at something with low
solids content somewhere in the in the
low 40s late 30s you might want to
include something like this or guar gum
which would increase the viscosity and
give you the effect of a thicker base
with higher solids
you can buy this off the shelving bar on
Amazon eBay Health Food Shops anywhere
you like it's available all over the
place
that is all of the ingredients in there
it's it's great like I said I'm not I'm
not associated with special ingredients
I just find their products easy to buy
readily available a little bit on the
expensive side for what they are but if
you're just making ice cream at home you
don't need to go out and buy five kilos
of chromadan just to to make ice cream
on to the next one
xantham gun there we go xanthan gum
xantham gum has the proprietary number
of e415
what is it it's actually a ferment part
fermented sugar
um
but it is really good on its own it's a
really decent stabilizer if you don't
want to get in too much into stabilizers
and you just want something that you can
put in your ice cream to help with a bit
of everything
I'd probably go with this you can
it will help with an increased viscosity
it's okay at dealing with ice crystals
size and formulation and it's also okay
at reducing the air bubble size because
of the viscosity increase
it's readily available like I said it's
cheap you can buy it basically
everywhere it's in so many foods out
there it's crazy it's
probably the easiest one to get out of
all of these and the cheapest to I would
have thought so if you're just going to
start looking into stabilizers xantom
gum is probably where I'd start
now we're moving on to
these other two gelatin and pectin
gelatin
it's not too bad actually
um
another ice cream expert that I've
spoken to for years he started his ice
cream Journey using gelatin in basically
all of his recipes and I never actually
got to try it as ice cream he lives on
different part of the world to me but
you know rest assured other people have
and they say it's excellent so let's
assume the gelatin is really good I've
used it a couple of times
um
I find it okay to use I prefer to to use
this but it's each line
what does it do
it stabilizes the free water as all of
these do they stabilize free water as
well what does that mean
water and ice cream is what gives the
ice crystals the body is what makes it
cold is what assists with the mouth feel
gelatin will hold on to that free water
and form a gel gelatin gel it's in the
the clues in the name and it will stop
that free water
creating large ice crystals it will
assist with a small Ice Crystal
formation so what the result is your
mouth your tongue feels that the ice
cream is smoother and slightly warmer
now I say warm it's you know relative to
how cold ice cream should be anyway
that is what free water does too much
free water and ice cream will make it
really cold
and sometimes I'm sure you've had it
before you go somewhere you try some ice
cream and it hits your mouth and go oh
that really is cold and that's because
there's too much free water in that ice
cream itself
now I was lucky enough to go to a
Michelin star restaurant with the people
that I work with and the food was just
incredible I mean incredible I'll put a
little video up here of the final course
which was mint chocolate chip ice cream
this is not just any mint choc chip ice
cream hold on let me just get my best
marks and Spencer's voice going
this is not just any
this is Michelin star grade mint jockey
chip ice cream crap name but look at the
theatrics of it now one thing that I
actually said here was the ice cream is
really cold it had been taken out the
freezer to scoop into a nice little
quinell as you can see but when you ate
the ice cream it was really cold way too
cold very low in solids as well which
considering the the quality of the rest
of the food I guess it is what it is
but that free water in that ice cream
made it much colder than ice cream
should be the lower solids allowed that
free water to stay open in the recipe so
as it it may have been stabilized but if
it was it wasn't done particularly well
so
whatever that noise is so when you put
it in your mouth we were talking you
know a tiny little piece here of ice
cream you put it in your mouth the
instant knowledge the instant effect was
wow that's too cold rather than or what
a lovely creamy minty ice cream it was
just too cold
so the addition of any of these in
relation to the actual ice cream recipe
itself would have made it last a little
bit longer rather than melt so
incredibly quickly which is what it did
and it would go onto your tongue and it
would feel smoother more luxurious and a
little bit more temperature level
so all of these would have helped with
that
the last one we're going to talk about
here
that we have available is pectin
I don't think a lot of pectin as a
stabilite stabilizer it's okay
and again it does the same as this
pectin naturally occurring chemical in
Fruit so when you make jam what you're
doing is you're warming heating the
pectin which will then bond to the water
and thicken it up create a gel so that's
what happens in jams jellies marmalades
and conserves all that kind of thing
it's the pectin is thickening the
water and that's the same as agaric gas
the same as gelatin it's the same as
guar gum it's the same as xanthan gram
all these kind of things would do that
kind of thing as well but I find pectin
especially powdered stuff
it's you know it comes in these little
sachets it dissolves easy enough but
over the course of a couple of weeks in
the freezer it can actually go a bit
gritty so I tend to not use this I just
use it if I'm making
a liquid base or add in for an ice cream
so these are the ones that we've got
here at home we've got some others
commercial ones that we're not going to
delve into too much today but
something to also remember is some
people will say that ice cream is
stabilized by sugar and that is to a
degree correct sugar will stabilize a
lot of the free water and turn it into
you know if you make
um
a syrup a sugar syrup for various
different things that is stabilized
water
you're evaporating some of the water off
you're bonding the sugar molecules into
the water molecules and you're
stabilizing it
it's the same thing so if you really
don't want to use stabilizers then my
Approach would be to increase the sugars
slightly to help stabilize some of that
free water
the one final thing that I've not
brought on here which I'm just going to
pop down here and get
[Music]
child proof love it
milk powder
uh milk powder is a great stabilizer
it's is quite basic in its abilities it
does the same as as a lot of the
viscosity increasing stabilizers it
bonds onto the free water but it has the
it has the difference compared to the
other two of increasing solids so
milk powder is borderline essential for
ice creams and I get really confused
when I see people make ice cream and
sell it and it doesn't have things like
this in or
um CNC or maltodextrin or something
because
if you just use milk and cream and
whatever other ingredients you know
you're adding liquid wise along with
your sugar it's very difficult to get
your solids where you need them to be
even in England where we have a 50 fat
cream so double cream fifty percent fat
the milk solids is still extremely low
so if you used a standard milk and cream
recipe with sugar let's just say it's
vanilla and you add vanilla extract
then what you've got is a standard
sugar content let's let's just say 15 16
sugar you've then got your fat content
which might be 15 16 fat as well you've
got your solids content that might be
somewhere in the 40 range maybe early
40s but your milk
solids non-fat milk solids so you'll see
that as in
msnf other recipe milk solids non-fat
they'll be really low that'll be in a
five percent range
and that's too low because you haven't
got enough milk protein or lactose in
there so the addition of milk powder
for dairy-based ice creams is kind of
essential and this is the problem with a
lot of vegan recipes is you can't do
this
you can't add this so you have to find
another way to add solids to a vegan
recipe you have to ignore the milk
solids element because you're using
other ingredients and there are some
very very clever science based
and we've we've
um spoken about some of them before
we've done some of the recipes as a
lovely woman called Chiara who lives in
Italy she specializes she's she is
actually a scientific expert on vegan
ice cream so I'll put a link below she
does courses as well so that might be
interesting for you to hit up if you're
vegan if you really want to know about
the scientific element of ice cream it's
good to um good to learn from multiple
people
but she has lots of different things
that she adds in to make her gelato so
she doesn't really make
American ice cream she makes gelato you
can't use this so that's something to
consider if you're a vegan and you're
making ice cream
the the final element I'll touch on here
is
using off-the-shelf products you can
achieve a decent result so you can just
go out and buy milk cream milk powder
sugar and whatever flavoring you want to
use beer that vanilla or chocolate or
whatever you can combine them without
any of these and produce really good ice
cream much better than Ben and Jerry's
and Haagen-Dazs because you're making it
there and then it hasn't had that
thought refreeze cycle that a lot of
those doers are being transported it's
made to your desire your need you know
you want my high sugar moment low sugar
you can make it as you want it it will
always be better than off the shelf
always I guarantee it
if you want to take it to the next level
and you want to make a larger batch
then start looking at stabilizers not
necessarily that one because you need to
use that anyway
the the final part of this video is what
do they do what stabilizers actually do
is allow ice cream to last longer
defrost slower capture free water and
increase viscosity that's what they do
if you are at home you've got let's say
you've got a two liter ice cream machine
which is quite big for a home ice cream
machine you make a two liter batch and
in reality you only eat maybe two or
three hundred mil or two three hundred
grams a week all of that ice cream is
going to go in the freezer every time
you open it up you're increasing the
temperature in the freezer your ice
cream is ever so slightly melting it's
then refreezing which is increasing the
Ice Crystal size increasing the air
bubble size
and it's actually making the texture
worse and after a month or two you're
literally going to open the tub and eat
a nice old icy chunk of ice cream and
it's not going to be pleasant
these will help with that I did a
s'mores video
last week released that last week that
had been in for weeks in the freezer due
to personal issues and filming the
actual result and it was just as good as
the day it was made because it was
stabilized so that's what they do a nice
little touch not too in-depth in
scientific as to what they do there are
a couple of website recommendations and
that is dream Scoops I'll put links to
all of these below so you can go and
have a really good read about what the
chemical structure is how they work
together and you know it's quite an
in-depth subject you can get really lost
into stabilizers if you want to so
you've got dream Scoops that talk about
it in a reasonable amount of depth
you've got ice cream calc no ice cream
calculator but the website's called ice
cream count and he goes into a lot of
detail about stabilizers as well you've
got underbelly they talk about ice cream
stabilizers so I'll put links to those
below if this is your kind of thing and
you want to know how to better
mouth feel of your ice cream and the
lasting effects of your ice cream
especially if you're making it
commercially you absolutely should be
stabilizing your ice cream
then head down here have a look ask any
questions you might have and if you want
to know about commercial stabilizers in
depth then we can do another video about
those but I want to thank you all for
listening to this little video about ice
cream stabilizers hopefully it's not
confused you too much I tried to keep it
as simple as I could
and
thanks very much for watching don't
forget to like And subscribe and if you
want to support the channel then we have
Kofi I'll put a link below and this is
the symbol here you can head over and
offer your support in any way you fancy
it really helps keep the channel going
and we will see you next week
[Music]
together